in the smaller Gate 3 cleric class guide
I'm going to be covering the cleric
class including all seven subclasses and
providing you some useful information
I'll be doing more build guides
including those for cleric later but for
now let's look at how a cleric functions
and its basics
clerics are Divine spellcasters in bg3
that are in tune with their chosen deity
they specialize in healing and
supporting magic but they can also cast
offensive spells and do fairly well in
martial combat for a full spellcaster
they have proficiencies in light and
medium armor as well as Shields and
simple weapons and morning Stars which
is the most of any full spellcaster in
bg3 and some subclasses or domains even
provide them with heavy armor and
martial weapon proficiencies putting
them on par with even the best martial
classes in this regard some clerics lean
more to the melee side of things when it
comes to martial combat because they can
cast inflict wounds which is a meleely
ranged spell that deals fantastic damage
our assume will prefer to forego the use
of this spell and play at longer ranges
clerics can also use Channel Divinity
every short rest varying greatly
depending on their subclass which can
often turn the tide of battle and is
extremely powerful in some cases
in this section we'll take a look at how
to set up your cleric during character
creation for best results we'll begin
with abilities first since this is
arguably the most important part aside
from choosing your subclass
your primary ability as a cleric is
wisdom wisdom determines how difficult
it is for an enemy to save against your
spells and prove spell attack roles
improves wisdom skill checks and wisdom
saving throws as well as increases the
amount of prepared spells a cleric can
have
Constitution is there to help keep you
alive via HP and also to help you
maintain concentration on spells like
bless pain or protection from energy
should you get hit while concentrating
on them
for this reason I strongly recommend
that you invest 16 into wisdom and at
least 14 in Constitution during
character creation 14 dexterity is also
not bad if you plan to use medium armor
or if you plan to play a more ranged
clearing you could instead take 16
strength if you plan to play a subclass
with heavy armor proficiency and plan to
play melee when not casting spells the
choice is up to you
I've listed out two ways you can set up
your cleric one if you're going to use
strength and the other if you want to
use dexterity
note that I've changed this from the
recommendations of the game as it's more
optimized during the early going
when it comes to race elf is not bad for
some extra weapon proficiencies if you
don't go Tempest or war and perception
proficiency and Fey ancestry
they also gain dark vision which can
help you land your attacks in Dark
Places and what else also gain stealth
proficiency and increased movement speed
human is also not bad if you want a
couple more weapon proficiencies if not
Tempest or war and another skill
proficiency
Lightfoot halflings are another solid
choice because they re-roll if they roll
a 1 on any attack roll ability check or
saving throw all but preventing them
from ever critically missing they also
cannot be frightened easily and have
advantage on stealth checks drow have
Superior dark vision Fey ancestry and
perception proficiency which are all
decent pickups for the cleric and half
work is also a good choice especially
for melee focused clerics since they
have dark vision Relentless endurance
and Savage attacks for skills you'll
likely focus on wisdom-based skills
since that's what you'll have a good
amount of your ability points if you
take the folk hero background and an L
for drow for a race you can select
Insight in medicine and have Proficiency
in all wisdom skills
next let's look at cleric progression
and things that all clerics gain
at level 1 clerics gain level 1 spells
along with two level one spell slots and
three can trips they will also learn
some domain spells based on the domain
they selected though these might be
better versions of spells they already
know
that clerics need to prepare their
spells and can cast any spell they know
as long as they have the spell slot for
it and it's prepared also at this level
clerics will choose a subclass and gain
domain spells and a subclass feature
based on their selection we'll cover
these more in the subclasses section but
for now let's focus on things all
clerics get while leveling and finally
at this level clerics will choose their
deity the full extent of What Choosing
each deity does in game is not currently
known but you should select one based on
the principles that best match your own
or best match the ideals of the
character you are role playing
at level 2 all clerics will gain one
channel Divinity charge and will be able
to use their Channel Divinity class
future once per short rest
this feature varies from subclass to
subclass for instance life domain
clerics gain preserve life which is an
AOE heel while light domain clerics gain
Radiance of the Dawn which is a radiant
damage AOE we'll cover what these are
more in the subclasses section at the
same level all clerics gain turn Undead
which uses a channel Divinity charge to
make all in debt around them flee if
they fail a wisdom saving throw this
lasts three turns or until they take
damage
at level 3 clerics gain access to level
2 spells and gain level 2 spell slots
and can upcast level 1 spells with these
slots if they can be many spells in bg3
can be upcast for additional damage or
increased targets pay attention to which
spells they are so you don't waste
higher level spell slots on ones that
can't be at level 4 clerics gained their
first feat ability Improvement is not a
bad choice to further boost their wisdom
allowing them to land their spells more
easily and prepare an additional spell
however both resilient Constitution and
warcaster are also not bad options since
clerics have a fair number of
concentration spells and they are likely
to be in melee range particularly if
they went the strength route
also at this level clerics can select an
additional can trip from their cantrip
list
at level 5 clerics gain access to level
3 spells and gain level 3 spell slots
and can upcast level 1 and 2 spells with
these slots if they can be
also at this level clerics gain destroy
Undead which makes it so they deal
radiant damage whenever they
successfully turn and Undead using their
turn on dead class feature
at level 6 all clerics will gain a
subclass feature based on their chosen
domain we'll cover what these are more
in the subclasses section
and also at this level clerks will gain
a second Channel Divinity charge
allowing them to use their Channel
Divinity class feature or turn Undead
twice in between short rests at level 7
clerics gain access to level 4 spells
and game level 4 spell slots and they
can upcast level one two and three
spells with these slots if they can be
at level 8 clerics will gain either
Divine strike or potent spell casting
depending on which domain they selected
during character creation
Divine strike will add one to eight
damage to their weapon attack once per
turn and the damage type this deals
depends on the domain chosen boat and
spell casting allows the cleric to add
their wisdom modifier to the damage of
their cleric cantrips further boosting
their damage these are sacred flame and
produce Flame
also at this level clerics gain their
second feat they can choose ability
Improvement or one of the others I
suggested Elemental Adept is also not a
bad choice if you went light or Tempest
domains
at level 9 clerics gain access to level
5 spells and gain level 5 spell slots
and can upcast level one two three and
four spells with these slots if they can
be
at level 10 all clerics gain divine
intervention to invoke the aid of their
deity which they can use one time and
never again in the whole game there are
four interventions you can choose from
arm thy servant creates and equips the
devotee space
golden generosity creates a chest
containing camp supplies and around 10
potions and elixirs opulent Revival will
resurrect all Fallen companions with
half their hit points and restore them
as if they had long rested with an 18
meter radius and Sunder the heretical
deals 8d10 radian damage to All Enemies
within 15 meters if they fail a wisdom
saving throw and if they succeed then
they still take half damage at level 11
clerics gain access to level 6 spells
and gain one level 6 spell slot and can
upcast level one two three four and five
spells with this slot if they can be
this is the highest level of spells
clerics can learn in pg3
at level 12 clerics gained their final
feat if you don't have wisdom to 20 yet
now would be a good time to do it with
ability Improvement otherwise consider
choosing one of the ones I've already
mentioned
clerics and bg3 have light and medium
armor proficiency as well as shield and
simple weapon proficiency so they have a
lot of options also as mentioned earlier
some subclasses also provide heavy armor
proficiency or even martial weapon
proficiency so cleric gear will vary
from cleric to cleric depending on
subclass it's likely your cleric will
wear medium or heavy armor to gain
maximum protection since they are
unlikely to have more than about 14 or
16 dexterity ruling out light armor
unless it has the great other bonuses
additionally they are likely to use a
shield since they can to further pad
their Armor class weapon wise they'll
use whatever they can that deals the
most damage that they have proficiency
with and if they went for dexterity over
strength they'll look to use a finesse
weapon and will likely want a good
ranged weapon as well
strength clerics will likely use sacred
flame when they cannot get into melee
range however
[Music]
choosing a cleric subclass in bg3 can be
quite challenging because there's a lot
of things to consider you want heavy
armor do you want martial weapon
proficiency do you want more offensive
spells do you want to focus more on
martial combat all these things can
influence which subclass to choose and
it's not immediately clear during
character creation what you're going to
get
at level 1 all cleric domains gain
features based on their domain as well
as two domain spells that are always
prepared
all clerics gain their Channel Divinity
feature at level 2 that will depend on
their domain Chosen and they will gain
two more domain Spells at every odd
level up through level 9. they will also
gain another subclass feature at level 6
and they will either gain Divine strike
or potent spell casting at level 8.
let's take a look at life clerics first
at level 1 life clerics gain heavy armor
proficiency allowing them to wear heavy
armor with no penalties to spell casting
or attack rolls
also at this level they gain disciple of
Life which adds two plus the Spells
level to the healing any spell does this
makes life clerics the most effective
healers in bg3
at level 2 life clerics gain preserve
life for their Channel Divinity class
feature this allows them to heal allies
in a 9 meter radius for three times
their character level
at level 6 life clerics gain blessed
healer which heals them for two plus the
spell level of any healing spell they
cast on another creature note that if
you cast an AOE heal you will heal for
each Target healed by your spell at
level 8 life clerics gain Divine strike
radiant adding 1 to 8 radiant damage to
their weapon attacks once per turn note
this applies to both ranged and melee
weapon attacks but does not apply to
unarmed attacks
additionally clerics gained their domain
Spells at levels one three five seven
and nine and you can see what they are
for the life cleric on the screen
let's take a look at a light cleric next
at level one light clerics will gain
warding Flair allowing them to use the
reaction to impose disadvantage on an
enemy that is about to hit them in
combat this can be used once per round
without limit making it a particularly
strong feature make sure to tick this to
on and to ask in your reaction to sap at
level 2 light clerics gain Radiance of
the dawn for their Channel Divinity
class future this allows them to strike
for 2d10 plus their character level
radiant damage in a 9 meter radius note
this will not hit allies only enemies
at level 6 light clerics will gain
improved warding flare allowing them to
impose disadvantage on an enemy
attacking an ally that is about to hit
them in combat this is a phenomenal
upgrade since you'll likely be able to
use this every turn at level 8 light
clerics get to add their wisdom modifier
to the damage of their cleric cantrips
further boosting the damage of these
These are sacred flame and produce flame
light clerics also gain their domain
Spells at levels one three five seven
and nine and you can see what these are
on the screen
next let's take a look at the trickery
domain cleric at level 1 trickery
clerics can grant another character
advantage on stealth checks as an action
as long as they maintain concentration
this is a great way to boost the stealth
of your roguish character if they don't
already have advantage on stealth checks
note that you cannot Target yourself
with this feature
at level 2 trickery clerics gain invoke
duplicity for their Channel Divinity
class feature this allows them to create
an illusion within 9 meters that grants
allies advantage on attacks made against
enemies standing within 3 meters of it
as long as the Ally is also standing
within three meters of it this requires
concentration to maintain and an action
to use making it very situational
at level 8 trickery clerics gain Divine
strike poison adding one to eight poison
damage to their weapon attacks once per
turn note this applies to both ranged
and melee weapon attacks but does not
apply to unarmed attacks
trickery domain clerics also gain their
domain Spells at levels one three five
seven and nine and you can see what
these are on the screen now
next up is knowledge domain at level 1
knowledge clerics gain expertise in two
of the following skills Arcana history
nature or religion note that you'll gain
expertise even if you don't have
Proficiency in these skills so it's best
not to take proficiencies in skills you
plan to select expertise in at level 2
knowledge clerics gain knowledge of the
ages for their Channel Divinity class
feature this allows them to gain
proficiency and all skills of one
ability until long rest much like the
Geth Yankees astral knowledge
[Music]
at level 8 knowledge clerics get to add
their wisdom modifier to the damage of
their clerican trips further boosting
their damage again these are sacred
flame and produce flame knowledge domain
clerics gain their domain Spells at
levels one three five seven and nine as
well and you can see what these are on
the screen now
[Music]
next are nature clerics at level 1
nature clerics gain heavy armor
proficiency allowing them to wear heavy
armor with no penalties to spell casting
or attack rolls
also at level 1 nature clerics get to
select one Druid can trip from Poison
spray produce flame shillelagh and Thorn
whip they also gain proficiency and
animal handling nature or survival
at level 2 nature clerics gain charm
animals and plants for their Channel
Divinity class feature this allows them
to try to charm animals and plants
within 9 meters of them preventing
enemies from attacking them it's one of
the weaker channel divinities in my
opinion but it's still nice to have
at level 8 nature clerics gained Divine
strike Elemental Fury adding one to
eight cold fire or lightning damage to
their weapon attacks once per turn note
this applies to both ranged and melee
weapon attacks but does not apply to
unarmed attacks nature clerics gained
their domain Spells at levels one three
five seven and nine and you can see what
those are on the screen now
next we'll take a look at Tempest domain
at level 1 Tempest clerics gain heavy
armor proficiency allowing them to wear
heavy armor with no penalties to spell
casting or attack rolls they also gain
martial weapon proficiency allowing them
to add their proficiency bonus to attack
Rolls made with any weapon since they
have simple weapon proficiency already
at level 1 Tempest clerics gain Wrath of
the storm which allows them to deal 2-16
thunder or lightning damage to an enemy
attacking them with a melee weapon
attack using their reaction if they fail
a saving throw they still deal half
damage if the target saves
at level 2 Tempest clerics gained
destructive wrath for their Channel
Divinity class feature this allows them
to use their Channel Divinity charge as
a reaction whenever they deal lightning
or thunder damage to ensure that they
deal the maximum damage with one of
those damage types for instance if a
tempest cleric uses call lightning which
normally deals 3 to 30 lightning damage
if the enemies inside its AOE fail their
save it would now deal the full 30
lightning damage to each charger that
failed their save and 15 to those that
didn't fail since they still take half
damage this is extremely deadly because
remember this replenishes on short rest
and after level 6 you can use it twice
before short rest
at level 6 Tempest clerics gain
Thunderbolt strike allowing them to push
enemies up to 3 meters when they deal
lightning or thunder damage to them they
can sometimes push enemies to their
death
at level 8 Tempest clerics gain Divine
strike Thunder adding one to eight
Thunder damage to their weapon attacks
once per turn
again note this applies to both ranged
and melee weapon attacks but does not
apply to unarmed attacks Tempest clerics
gain their domain Spells at levels one
three five seven and nine and you can
see what those are on the screen
and lastly we come to war domain at
level 1 War clerics gain heavy armor
proficiency allowing them to wear heavy
armor with no penalties to spell casting
or attack rolls they also gain martial
weapon proficiency allowing them to add
their proficiency bonus to attack roles
made with any weapon since again they
have simple weapon proficiency already
also a level 1 War clerics gained War
priest allowing them to use their bonus
action to make an attack they gained
three charges of this at level 1
increasing as the war priest gains
levels and replenishing after a long
rest note that you must take War domain
levels in order to increase your War
priest charges and that these are not
based on character level
at level 2 War domain clerics gained
guided strike for their Channel Divinity
class feature this allows them to gain a
plus 10 bonus to their attack role as a
reaction almost guaranteeing that it
connects
[Music]
at level 6 where the main clerics gained
War God's blessing which allows them to
use a channel Divinity charge to boost
the attack role of a nearby Ally by plus
10 as a reaction
and at level 8 Work lyrics gain Divine
strike weapon adding one to eight
slashing damage to their weapon attacks
once per turn note this applies to both
ranged and melee weapon attacks but does
not apply to unarmed attacks
War clerics gain their domain Spells at
levels one three five seven and nine and
you can see what these are on the screen
now
in this section of revolver's Gate 3
cleric class guide we'll take a look at
multi-classing of cleric in bg3 and what
other classes you might multi-class with
please keep in mind this is not a
complete list but rather helpful
suggestions that make good pairings
clerics have a lot to give at level 1 as
each domain provides a class feature and
sometimes heavy armor proficiency or
martial weapon proficiency
they also gain their Channel Divinity
feature at level 2 which is exceptional
in a lot of cases replenishing each
short rest if you don't multi-class at
level 1 or 2 the next likely place would
be after level 6 because each cleric
gains another subclass feature here as
well as a second Channel Divinity charge
however it really depends on the domain
you selected monks also multi-class
while level 6 since it gains subclass
features at this level and uses wisdom
for extra Armor class when not using
armor as well as for its spell DC when
using Wave the four elements spells so
is a great pairing circle of the spores
Druid is also not a bad option as it can
summon zombies at level 6 and give
itself temporary HP and boost its
damaging attacks with symbiotic entity
you can also use Aid to buff your
zombies so they don't die as easily and
Druids use wisdoms for their spells as
well or you could go five Circle the
land pick up lightning bolt which
combines well with seven Tempest Druid
for deadly damage thanks to destructive
Wrath Ranger also multi-classes well
with cleric thanks to using wisdom for
its spells too and you could take 5
levels of gloomstalker or Hunter to pick
up extra attack and then go seven levels
of cleric for level 4 cleric spells
increase Channel Divinity charges and
another subclass feature at level 6.
so that wraps up our clear class guide
and I hope you found this information
useful and it helps you make a better
decision about which cleric domain you
want to play when playing your cleric as
always we will have some builds coming
and if you have other tips that I forgot
to mention please leave them in the
comments or if you have questions please
leave them there as well
[Music]